

PhD Marco A. Lopez-Sanchez

Short bio: Marco is a postdoctoral researcher at Géosciences Montpellier - CNRS in France. He holds a *PhD* in Geology from the University of Oviedo in Spain. In the past, he combined jobs outside the academy as a Geology teacher and freelance geologist with postdoctoral training in the research group of Sergio Llana-Fúnez. Since the beginning of 2018, he is working with Andréa Tommasi in the *Manteau et Interfaces* research group in Montpellier, where his research focuses on characterisation of microstructure and texture during deformation and annealing processes using in-situ monitoring. Although in the past I worked mainly with quartzfeldspathic rocks, currently the materials I work with are olivine, ice, and magnesium.

Marco research interests include different aspects of geodynamic processes from microscopic to orogen-scale. His primary interests include rock deformation and rheology, crustal-scale shear zones, crustal strength modelling, characterization of rock microstructure/texture using EBSD and image analysis, and understanding strain localization in nature. Other interests are geological mapping and evolution of ancient orogens, the interaction between rock deformation, fluids and metamorphism, and the establishment of the absolute time at which deformation processes occur. I also enjoy programming for data analysis and a few other cool things.

Personal details

Full name: Marco Antonio López Sánchez

Work address:

Géosciences Montpellier - CNRS Université de Montpellier Campus Triolet cc060 Place Eugène Bataillon 34095 Montpellier Cedex05 France

Tel: (33) 4 67 14 30 64

e-mails:

&&& @umontpellier.fr (replace the triple ampersand symbol with *marco-antonio.lopez-sanchez*)

On the web

Personal website: https://marcoalopez.github.io/

CV (pdf): Resume_pdf

Orcid-ID: http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0261-9267

Research-ID: A-4290-2015 Scopus author ID: 56320859100 Google scholar: scholar.google

Publons: 1513594

Github page: https://github.com/marcoalopez

At Géosciences Montpellier: link

Education

Jul 2013 - *PhD* in Geology, *cum laude* honours, Department of Geology, Univ. of Oviedo.

Advisor: Sergio Llana-Fúnez. Co-advisors: Profs. Alberto Marcos and Francisco J. Martínez

Thesis: Análisis tectónico de la Falla de Vivero (Galicia, NW of Spain)

Sep 2007 - DEA (Masters of Science - *M.Sc.*) in Geology, Department of Geology, University of Oviedo. Project advisor: Prof. A. Marcos

Jan 2006 - Bachelor of Science (*B.Sc.*) in Geology, Department of Geology, University of Oviedo.

Research

Professional experience (only academic related)

2018 - present - Postdoctoral researcher, Géosciences Montpellier, Université de Montpellier

2015 - 2017 - Postdoctoral researcher, Dpto. de Geología, Universidad de Oviedo

2013 - 2015 - Research assistant (non-paid volunteer), Dpto. de Geología, Universidad de Oviedo

2007 - 2013 - *PhD candidate*, Departamento de Geología, Universidad de Oviedo

Fellowships/Awards

2017 - Postdoctoral fellowship Clarín-COFUND (Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions 7th FW) (2 years)

2017 - Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions Seal of Excellence Award with the research project proposal IDEA

2016 - Early Career Scientist's Travel Award for EGU General Assembly 2016

2007 - Predoctoral fellowship in the Severo Ochoa Program (FICYT, Principality of Asturias, Spain) (4 years)

Scientific activities as visitor researcher

2019 - **Grenoble (France)**. Duration: 1.5 months. Experimental ice deformation using digital image correlation methods at Institut des Géosciences de l'Environnement under the supervision of Maurine Montagnat.

2018 - **Saint-Étienne (France)**. Duration: 1 week. High temperature experimental deformation of Magnesium alloys (channel-die compression rig) at École des Mines de Saint-Étienne (collab. R. Quey).

Publications

In review or available as a pre-print

%-%-%

Published or in press (citable) peer-reviewed publications

PDF-08 **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (2018) GrainSizeTools: a Python script for grain size analysis and paleopiezometry based on grain size. *Journal of Open Source Software* **3**(30): 863, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00863

PDF-07 **Lopez-Sanchez MA** and Llana-Fúnez S (2018) A cavitation-seal mechanism for ultramylonite formation in quartzfeldspathic rocks within the semi-brittle field (Vivero fault, NW Spain). *Tectonophysics* **745**: 132-153 http s://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2018.07.026

PDF-06 **Lopez-Sanchez MA**, García-Sansegundo J, and Martínez, FJ (2018) The significance of early Permian and early Carboniferous U-Pb zircon ages in the Bossòts and Lys-Caillaouas granitoids (Pyrenean Axial Zone). *Geological Journal - in press*; https://doi.org/10.1002/gj.3283

PDF-05 **Lopez-Sanchez MA** and Llana-Fúnez S (2016) An extension of the Saltykov method to quantify 3D grain size distributions in mylonites *Journal of Structural Geology* **93**: 149-161; https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsg.2016.10.008

PDF-04 **Lopez-Sanchez MA**, Aleinikoff J, Marcos A, Martínez FJ, and Llana-Fúnez S. (2016) An example of low Th/U zircon overgrowths of magmatic origin in a late orogenic variscan intrusive: the San Ciprián Massif (NW Spain). *Journal of the Geological Society* **173**: 282-291; https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2015-071

PDF-03 **Lopez-Sanchez MA** and Llana-Fúnez S (2015) An evaluation of different measures of dynamically recrystallized grain size for paleopiezometry or paleowattmetry studies. *Solid Earth* **6**: 475-495, Special issue: Deformation mechanisms and ductile strain localization in the lithosphere; https://doi.org/10.5194/se-6-475-2015

PDF-02 **Lopez-Sanchez MA**, Marcos A, Martínez FJ, Llana-Fúnez S, and Iriondo A (2015) Setting new constrains on the age of crustal-scale normal fault (Vivero Fault): Implications for the evolution of Variscan orogeny in the Iberian Massif. *International Journal of Earth Sciences* **104**(4): 927-962; https://doi.org/10.1007/s00531-014-1119-1

PDF-01 **Lopez-Sanchez MA**, Iriondo A, Marcos A, and Martínez FJ (2015) A U-Pb zircon age (479±5 Ma) from the uppermost layers of the Ollo de Sapo Fm near Viveiro (NW Spain): implications for the duration of rifting-related Cambro-Ordovician volcanism in Iberia. *Geological Magazine* **152**(2): 341-350; https://doi.org/10.1017/S0016756814000272

López-Sánchez MA (2007) Estudio geológico de la Falla de Vivero y estructuras asociadas en la región de Guntín (Lugo, NO de la Península Ibérica). *Trabajos de Geología* **27**: 97-157 link

Field Trip guides

FT1 - Marcos A, Bastida F, Aller J, Fernández FJ, Llana-Fúnez S and **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (2011) DRT post-conference Fieldtrip Guide: West Asturian Leonese Zone, Cabo Ortegal, Malpica-Lamego Line. *Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT - Oviedo) meeting* 42 pp + map.

Meeting proceedings

- 2019 Lopez-Sanchez MA, Tommasi A, Barou, F and Quey R.
 Preliminary results on magnesium (AZ31) in situ annealing experiments in the SEM-EBSD. Final CREEP workshop (Les Houches France)
- 2017 Llana-Fúnez S, Alonso JL, Caldera N and Lopez-Sanchez
 MA. Fault rocks at the base of the Somiedo Nappe (Variscan Orogen, NW Spain). Deformation mechanisms, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT) 2017 (Inverness, Scotland)
- 2017 Llana-Fúnez S, de Paola N, Pozzi G and Lopez-Sanchez MA.
 Slip events propagating along a ductile mid-crustal strike-slip shear

- zone (Malpica-Lamego line, Variscan Orogen, NW Iberia). *European Geoscience Union General Assembly*
- 2016 **Lopez-Sanchez MA** and Llana-Fúnez S. Characterizing 3D grain size distributions from 2D sections in mylonites using a modified version of the Saltykov method (Oral). *European Geoscience Union General Assembly*
- 2016 Lopez-Sanchez MA and Llana-Fúnez S. Caracterización de la distribución 3D de tamaños de grano en milonitas a partir de secciones usando el método Saltykov y una extensión del mismo (Oral). Congreso Geológico Nacional de España
- 2012 -Lopez-Sanchez MA, Llana-Fúnez S, Marcos A and Martínez
 FJ. Deformation of quartz and feldspar at mid-crustal depths in an
 extensional normal fault (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster). European
 Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2012 Lopez-Sanchez MA, Iriondo A, Marcos A and Martínez FJ.
 Una edad de 478,7 Ma (U-Pb Shrimp-RG) en la Formación Ollo de Sapo: implicaciones para el volcanismo Cambro-Ordovícico de la Península Ibérica (Poster). Congreso Geológico Nacional de España
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, LLana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos A. Strain gradient recorded in the Penedo Gordo granite during extensional movement of crustal-scale Vivero Fault (NW Spain) (Poster). European Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2011 **López-Sánchez MA**, LLana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos A. Changes in deformation mechanism and neocrystallisation in granite during a MT-LP deformation (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster). Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics meeting (Oviedo)
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, Llana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos
 A. Microstructural Evolution in Quartz and Feldspar During Medium
 T Deformation (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster). The
 Interrelationships Between Deformation and Metamorphism
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, Marcos A, Martínez FJ and Llana-Fúnez S. Hangingwall Metamorphism Related to an Extensional Orogenscale Shear Zone: The Vivero Fault (NW of Spain) (Poster). The Interrelationships Between Deformation and Metamorphism
- 2010 López-Sánchez MA, Marcos A, Martínez FJ and Llana-Fúnez S. Microstructures from the footwall to the hangingwall in the Viveiro Shear Zone (NW of Iberian Peninsula) (Oral by invitation). Sociedade Geológica de Portugal, VIII Congresso Nacional de Geología.
- 2009 **López-Sánchez MA**. Deformation partitioning patterns and metamorphism of the Viveiro shear zone (Guntín, NW of Iberian Peninsula) (*Poster*). *Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics meeting* (*Liverpool*)

Selected scripts & codes

GrainSizeTools: A free and open-source Python script for estimating the grain size from thin sections

Developed and maintained by ${\bf Lopez\text{-}Sanchez}~{\bf MA}$ (stable)

Info. & download: http://marcoalopez.github.io/GrainSizeTools/

mtex scripts: matlab scripts for use with the MTEX toolbox

Developed and maintained by Lopez-Sanchez MA (under development)

Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/mtex scripts

Strength envelopes: A Python script to generate crust and lithosphere strength envelopes

Developed and maintained by **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (under development) Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/Strength envelopes

JASPE: Just Another Stereoplot (in a) Python Environment

Developed and maintained by **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (under development)

Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/JASPE

Nearest neighbour: A Python script to estimate nearest neighbour distance and perform nearest neighbour Monte Carlo simulations
Developed and maintained by **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (stable)
Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/nearest_neighbour

into a dominoud. https://grindo.com/marcodropez/nearest_neighbour

Chemical age script: A free and open-source script to estimate the 'chemical'

ages in monazites analyzed in electron microprobes

Developed by **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (currently abandoned)

Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/chemical age script/

Selected training courses

2018 - Thematic School - Recrystallization Mechanism in Materials

Duration: 3 days, Saint-Étienne, France

Coordinator: Maurine Montagnat

Organized by the CNRS "Groupement de Recherche" on Recrystallization

(GDR3436)

2016 - Thematic School - Recrystallization Mechanism in Materials

Duration: 5 days (32 hours), Sète, France

Coordinator: Maurine Montagnat

Organized by the CNRS "Groupement de Recherche" on Recrystallization

(GDR3436). Certificate

2015 - Introduction to R Programming

Duration: 10 hours

Instructor: Filip Schouwenaars

Microsoft edx course (DAT204x). Certificate

2013 - Introduction to computer science and programming using Python

Duration: 210 hours

Prof. Eric Grimson, Prof. John Guttag, Dr Chris Terman and Dr Larry Rudolph Massachusetts Institute of Technology edx course (MITx - 6.00x). Certificate

2012 - Scanning Electron Microscopy and its applications to analyses of Rocks

Duration: 30 hours

Prof. John Wheeler, Dr Elisabetta Mariani and Dr Dan Tatham

Department of Earth, Ocean and Ecological Sciences, University of Liverpool

2008 - Training course in microtectonics

Duration: 30 hours Prof. Cees W. Passchier

Institut für Geowissenschaften; Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz

(Germany).

Analytical/technical skills

- Scientific computing and programming. Wide experience using
 Python programming language and the scientific libraries Numpy,
 Scipy, Matplotlib, and Pandas. I am also familiar with the basics of R
 and Matlab, version control systems such as Git, and code
 repositories such as GitHub.
- Image acquisition and analysis.
 - Good theoretical background and practical experience with cameras and digital image acquisition. Dcraw knowledge (for raw image extraction).
 - Experience using ImageJ and Scikit-Image (Python library) for image analysis, as well as developing my own codes. Noise reduction methods, image enhancement, grain segmentation, shape descriptors, grain size, and spatial analysis. For grain size analysis I use my own tools/scripts. See an example in http://marcoalopez.githu b.io/GrainSizeTools/
 - Experience with Digital Image Correlation (DIC)
 methods. Generation and quality analysis of speckle
 patterns (via image autocorrelation). DIC software's used:
 DICe, 7D and DICToolbox.
- Experimental deformation. Experience in experimental deformation using in-situ monitoring. Experience in sample preparation (ice, magnesium, rocks). Basic experience with welding and Labview engineering software.
- Scanning Electron Microscopy (BSD, Backscatter diffraction EBSD) data treatment.
 - Wide experience using the MTEX Matlab toolbox. I contributed to the MTEX through community scripts. See also https://github.com/marcoalopez/mtex_scripts
 - Others: AZtecHKL/Channel 5 and PFch5 script
- Electron Probe Micro-analyser (EPMA). Including monazite chemical dating (see https://github.com/marcoalopez/chemical_age_ script)
- Good theoretical background in interpreting experimental data (i.e. statistics, interpolation and regression)

- Experience in geological mapping and Geographical Information Systems (GIS)
- U-Pb geochronological data treatment

Participation in Research Projects

2018 - present ANR DREAM - Dynamic REcrystallization in Anisotropic Materials. Project led by Maurine Montagnat. Ref. *ANR-13-BS09-0001-01*

2016 - 2017

Cataclasis y fracturación en rocas de la corteza continental (*Cataclasis and rock fracturing in the continental crust*). Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez Ref. *MINECO-15-CGL2014-53388-P*

2015

Procesos geológicos modeladores del relieve de la cordillera cantábrica. Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez Ref. *FC-15-GRUPIN14-44*

2010 - 2014

La transición frágil-dúctil de la corteza del NO penínsular (*The brittle-ductile transition in the continental crust in North-western Iberia*). Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez *Ref. MICINN-10-CGL2010-14890*

2007 - 2010

The tectonic evolution of an orogen in the transition between the internal and external zones: A comparison between the Variscan orogen in the NW of Iberian Peninsula and the Pyreneean Axial Zone (original title in Spanish). Project led by Alberto Marcos. *Ref. CGL2006-08822/BTE*

Teaching (at university level)

Accredited as an assistant teacher by the National Agency for Quality Assessment and Accreditation of Spain (ANECA) in 2016

Graduate teaching assistant from **2009** to **2011** and in **2017** at Universidad de Oviedo

Laboratory sections taught: Plate Tectonics (30 hours); Structural Geology (20 hours); Geophysical and Geochemical prospecting (10 hours); Interpretation of geological maps (10 hours)

Field Camp taught: *Geodynamics (10 hours); Structural Geology (10 hours);* Fieldwork (geological mapping) (12.5 hours); Tectonics (10 hours); Structural analysis (5 hours)

Administrative experience

Deformation mechanisms, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT2011) meeting organizing committee. DRT meetings are a series of biannual international meetings dedicated to the study of deformation processes in rocks at different scales, from the microscale to the study of bulk deformation of the lithosphere

Languages

Spanish and Galician - mother tongue English - fluent French and Portuguese - elementary

Last update: 2019/01/25

Copyright © 2018; Header image ("the road") by Kamil Lehmann on Unsplash

(CC0)

Hosted on GitHub Pages — Created with Typora